Vlad Tabakov

Berlin, Germany | vl.tab.kov@gmail.com | +49 178 4782400 | linkedin.com/in/vlad-tabakov

Summary

Backend Team Lead with more than 5 years of experience in python web development, across many different libraries and tech blending understanding of infrastructure and backend with focus on data security and performance. I have led small teams of engineers working with health-related data APIs and scaling to multiple regions.

Skills

Programming: Python, Django, PostgreSQL, MariaDB, Docker, REST, FastAPI, RabbitMQ, Celery

AWS: Multi-AZ, Lambda, ECS, Glue, DMS, Redshift, Organizations, RDS, KMS, Pulumi IaC, Terraform

Miscellaneous: Typescript, Neo4J, Pandas, GIS, Ansible Languages: Russian (N1), English (C2), German (B1)

Experience

Backend&Cloud Team Lead, Mika Health – Berlin, Germany *Django, AWS, Terraform, Mariadb, Redis, Celery*

Sep 2022 - Present

- Spearheaded deployment of highly available, resilient and HIPAA compliant AWS cloud deployment of the backend (ECS, Pulumi IaC), achieved 0 downtime, 0 incident infrastructure change.
- Redesigned push notification infrastructure to reduce number of incidents, supporting 100k+ custom notifications/day;
- Promoted from remote freelance backend engineer to the backend & cloud team lead within 2 years;
- Hired and led a small team of backend and cloud engineers, conducted regular performance reviews, planned a tech debt reduction strategy and refined sprint tickets.

Backend engineer, Whalemap – Istanbul, Turkey *Django, EKS, FastAPI, Postgres, plotly*

May 2022 – Sep 2022

- Improved short-term user satisfaction score by 20%, overhauling authentication system and preventing regularly occurring login issues;
- Introduced test pipeline optimizations and parallel execution that sped up development time by 15%;
- Created a tool for rendering analytical dashboards using backend that improved marketing email campaign outreach.

Backend engineer, Balance platform – Moscow, Russia *RabbitMO*, *Flask*, *FastAPI*, *Postgres*, *Docker*

Mar 2020 – May 2022

- Streamlined a user application process in mortgage space via Whatsapp messenger, project with more than 5000 applications signed;
- Developed a strategy to eliminate technical debt across the backend department that improved burndown rate by 30%;
- Built Flask API microservices in new and existing projects.

Junior Data engineer, Transportation consultancy agency (IRTS) – Moscow, Russia Flask, Numpy, Pandas, selenium, Ixml, pyQT

Aug 2018 – Mar 2020

- Built a native app using PyQT that ran transportation models that introduced a new visual step in the customer outreach process;
- Improved gravitation matrix and pathfinding algorithm speed by several hours using numpy, pandas and scipy to automate existing MS Excel models;
- Automated a data retrieval pipeline used in Big Data transportation models using multiprocessing, lxml, selenium and SQLite, reduced execution time by 2 days;

Education

Moscow State University of Transport, BS in Economics

Sept 2015 - May 2019